<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Intuitive Coding</title><description>I quit my job and moved to Panama to learn to code. This is my blog.</description><link>http://localhost:2369/</link><image><url>http://localhost:2369/favicon.png</url><title>Intuitive Coding</title><link>http://localhost:2369/</link></image><generator>Ghost 1.6</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:16:12 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2369/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>What is programming?</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When historians look back on our time here on earth, it's not going to be the computers that they remember. Programming is about a new way of thinking, a way of expressing ourselves which we simply didn't need before the invention of computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've always been able to say &amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2369/what-is-programming/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">59973cc59fa1f20f15e45891</guid><category>me</category><dc:creator>Zachary Bluedorn</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 22:26:51 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2017/12/eval_apply_compressed.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2017/12/eval_apply_compressed.jpg" alt="What is programming?"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When historians look back on our time here on earth, it's not going to be the computers that they remember. Programming is about a new way of thinking, a way of expressing ourselves which we simply didn't need before the invention of computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've always been able to say &amp;quot;what is&amp;quot;. But we've never been very good at saying &amp;quot;how to.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gerald Sussman, computer science professor at MIT and author of the classic &lt;a href="http://sarabander.github.io/sicp/"&gt;Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs&lt;/a&gt;, gives a compelling talk about the role of programming in the grander scheme of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fAY0_pesZ6s?rel=0&amp;start=435&amp;end=660&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, we've always had natural languages to describe facts about the world. Most of the knowledge we have can be described as declarative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="declarativeknowledge"&gt;Declarative knowledge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="orwhatistrue"&gt;Or, what is true&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;√x is the y such that y² = x and y ≥ 0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Declarative knowledge tells us what, but it doesn't tell us how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for thousands of years we've also had algorithms, formal steps describing how to accomplish some goal. We can describe this type of knowledge as imperative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="imperativeknowledge"&gt;Imperative knowledge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="orhowtodosomething"&gt;Or, how to do something&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;To find an approximation to √x
* Make a guess, G
* Improve the guess by averaging G and x / G
* Keep improving the guess until it is good enough
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference is that we now have programming languages that allow us to explain ideas in a way that even a dumb machine can understand us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="programming"&gt;Programming&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id="usingtheschemelanguage"&gt;Using the Scheme language&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can write the same imperative knowledge about how to computer a square root using a modern programming language. Here's how we would compute a square root using the Scheme language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-scheme"&gt;(define (sqrt x)
  (define (improve guess)
    (average guess (/ x guess)))
  (define (good-enough? guess)
    (&amp;lt; (abs (- (square guess) x))
       .001))
  (define (try guess)
    (if (good-enough? guess)
        guess
        (try (improve guess))))
  (try 1))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expressing our ideas as programs forces us to understand them at a deeper level than with natural languages (the language of mathematics included). And that's why programming is &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. Machines are unforgiving, and if we don't understand the solution well enough, the program simply won't work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the benefits of learning to code make it worth the struggle. Once you learn how it &amp;quot;feels&amp;quot; to understand a program, there's no going back. You realize there are lots of subjects you don't understand as well as you thought you did, and you start to bring the same mental rigor to them as well. And in the end, you understand things more deeply than you could before you learned to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Learning to Learn</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coding seems to me like the closest we'll ever get to magic. You whisper nonsense into some device, and if you get the words exactly right, the machine does what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always wanted to learn how to code. The problem for me was actually &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2369/learning-to-learn/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">59973cc59fa1f20f15e45888</guid><category>me</category><dc:creator>Zachary Bluedorn</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2017 03:50:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2017/08/learning_to_learn_compressed.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2017/08/learning_to_learn_compressed.jpg" alt="Learning to Learn"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coding seems to me like the closest we'll ever get to magic. You whisper nonsense into some device, and if you get the words exactly right, the machine does what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always wanted to learn how to code. The problem for me was actually &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, I heard that there were lots of great places online to learn how to code. There was &lt;a href="https://www.w3schools.com/"&gt;w3schools&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.codecademy.com/"&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt;, and thousands of other sites on Google. The trouble with these sites is that they never tell you how to actually &lt;em&gt;build&lt;/em&gt; anything on your own - how to sit down and write a real program, and how any of it works. I tried to learn how to code their way for awhile, but eventually I got tired of memorizing functions and not seeing how it all fit together. So I gave up, and decided that coding wasn't for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a freshman in college, I gave it another try. I took the &amp;quot;Introduction to Computer Science&amp;quot; class, which did nothing but make me never want see another line of code again. Our greasy-haired professor looked at us condescendingly. Why didn't we understand pointers and recursion? To him, it was easy. And of course it was easy for him - he'd been coding for years. But we hadn't learned it yet, and he'd rather be writing his own code than teaching us. Looking around the classroom showed two groups of students. There were those who were confused, like me, and those who had given up completely and were just scrolling through Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily for me, I had one more introduction to coding in my previous job at Medallia. In managed services, we spent most of our time in meetings, but every once in awhile we'd have to write some code to do something special for the client. A report that showed which customer segment was most likely to repurchase. A chart that showed which business units were the best at resolving customer complaints, to highlight potential learnings. Most people had little interest in coding these sorts of things, and just took their problems to people like me who did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In doing more of these smaller projects, I got to learn what coding really was without the bias I had in college. I realized it's about solving problems. It's about building things. And it's about discovering insights that have never been noticed before, insights that change the way people think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I had perspective and could see the big picture, it became much easier to learn the theory behind how everything worked. I didn't have to struggle with learning like I had before, because I saw the value in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to have impact, learning to code is a great way to do it. I'm a student myself, but I plan to start building out this site to help us learn together. That means writing posts where I feel qualified, and linking to quality resources where I don't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started learning how to program, it was hard to see how the huge web of ideas all fit together. As I continue to learn, I'll be building &lt;a href="https://coggle.it/diagram/WWg7Q6-MpgABHUJI/11b6d8c496efa8e5d0c730207331a8756598db54c3d962fe4c6e4d0f59067e80"&gt;the map below&lt;/a&gt; of the big picture as I see it. The idea is to put links to the best sources of information and explanations that I've been able to find by combing through Quora, Reddit, and Hackernews, so that hopefully you are able to learn things a lot faster than me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2017/08/Learning_Path.png" alt="Learning to Learn"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Something New</title><description>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;How long do these things usually last?&amp;quot; I asked the customer service rep in my broken Spanish. &amp;quot;Oh, they usually blow over in a couple hours or so. But the power? Who knows,&amp;quot; he shrugged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to get service for my phone today. I'm a&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2369/something-new/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">59973cc59fa1f20f15e45887</guid><category>me</category><dc:creator>Zachary Bluedorn</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 03:47:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2017/08/stop_wasting_time_1650.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded>&lt;div class="kg-card-markdown"&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2017/08/stop_wasting_time_1650.jpg" alt="Something New"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;How long do these things usually last?&amp;quot; I asked the customer service rep in my broken Spanish. &amp;quot;Oh, they usually blow over in a couple hours or so. But the power? Who knows,&amp;quot; he shrugged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to get service for my phone today. I'm a techie, and I feel completely isolated without service. Add in the fact that I don't speak Spanish well, and not having a working cell phone means I'm about one loud noise away from a panic attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the day I made a plan for how I was going to ask for a service plan without really using too many words. The idea was to get to the phone store at the mall, point at my phone, and kind of make some gestures which would make it clear I needed data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I left my apartment around noon, and two and a half hours later, I learned two things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, Panama City has traffic. &lt;em&gt;Real&lt;/em&gt; traffic. Not &amp;quot;a little rubber necking after an accident&amp;quot; traffic, but more like &amp;quot;every intersection completely gridlocked, motorcycles coming from out of nowhere&amp;quot; traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the rain here means business. You see, Panama has two seasons - hot and dry, and hot and wet. And we're in the hot and wet season. When it rains, it's like a hurricane is tearing through, and in this instance it was enough to take the power out for the entire mall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just two weeks ago, I was sitting at my desk at &lt;a href="http://www.medallia.com/"&gt;Medallia&lt;/a&gt;, a software company in Palo Alto, the heart of Silicon Valley. I love Medallia, and am excited to watch it continue to grow. It has an incredible culture, full of people who deeply care about what they're doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I've always had this burning desire to travel, to pick up Spanish, to just see what else was out there. And I just didn't think I could do it as a services consultant for a tech startup starting to build out its practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I made the decision to take some time off and try something new, to see a different culture, and to study some of the subjects I never got around to in college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sold my stuff, cancelled my Hulu subscription, and moved to Panama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://localhost:2369/content/images/2017/08/panama.jpg" alt="Something New"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I'm new here, I don't speak much Spanish yet, I still don't have phone service, and I'm starting to see why they say that &amp;quot;things just take longer in Latin America.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I have lots of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>